Records of the Education Sector
World Bank Group Archives
- Policy and best practice development, 1965, 1969, 1972 - 2003; WB IBRD/IDA WB_IBRD/IDA_88-07; 15.01 linear feet of textual records
  Architectural standards records are organized by country or region. Several files relate to primary school building programs, urban primary schools, low-cost school and housing design, and community development and education centers. Internal memoranda from Lewis to regional staff to share information and details on prototype designs and features, costs, partners, village involvement, progress reported, and occasionally, brief mention of IDA education projects. There are also outgoing letters to UNESCO regional office education officials. Other records within the files include: costing or budget sheets; external reports or manuals, many of which were prepared by the UNESCO Regional Office for Education in Asia and UNESCO Regional Office for Education in Africa, and in Latin America and Caribbean; external reports of country ministries or research institutes; and an architects' brief. The external reports are mostly in English, French, and Farsi.
  UNESCO project preparation guidelines
  Also included in the series are records related to UNESCO guidelines for project preparation including a 1965 UNESCO low-cost school building report and recommendations, and a 1969 UNESCO report. There is also a substantive briefing note on UNESCO and World Bank relations in the education sector that was prepared by the Education and Employment Division, Population and Human Resources Department (PHREE) in 1988.
  Other guidelines subject files
  There are numerous other educational guidelines subject files maintained between 1973 and 1983 regarding data collection, project management, educational use of mass media, labor requirements model, education and manpower model, review of education lending (FY1979 - 1983), summary list of projects, and other topics.
  The more recent policy development subject files (1990 to 2001) relate to: Education for All Fast Track initiative (EFA-FTI); girls' education; Development Assistance Committee (DAC) goals; Africa Region education action plan and sector overview; and Task Force on Bridging the Digital Divide through Education.
  External Advisory Panels
  The series also contains records related to the establishment and dissemination of reports from advisory groups between 1978 and 2003. The External Advisory Group on Training for the Education Sector was appointed by Bank President McNamara in late 1977 to review the status of education in the developing world including the Bank's education and training lending and projects and to recommend areas for future action. The panel was chaired by David E. Bell of the Ford Foundation. Records related to the final report of this panel were maintained in the Non-Regional Information Center (NRIC) and consist of a single file (1978 - 1980). The NRIC file contains mostly internal memoranda to and from Director Habte regarding comments on the panel report issued in 1978 and input from the Regions including from R.K. Johnson, chief Education Division, East Asia and Pacific Region (AEPED). There are also letters between Chair David E. Bell and President McNamara regarding completion of the final report and from Habte to panel members announcing the 1979 Education Sector Strategy paper and follow up on the panel recommendations. Also included is a letter from Vice President Willi A. Wapenhans, East Africa Regional Office to the Tanzanian minister of education regarding a requested visit of the recently formed advisory panel to Tanzania.
  Records also reflect the establishment and activities of subsequent advisory panels formed annually to advise the Bank on the future direction in education covering the period 1994 to 2003. The 1994 to 1995 correspondence andbackground notes relates to the formation of the first annual panel formed in 1996. Records were primarily maintained by the Human Development Department Education Team (HDDED) Manager, later Director Maris O'Rourke. Correspondence is in the form of all-in-1 notes and email hard copies and facsimiles between O'Rourke, HDD Director David de Ferranti, HDD senior staff, and letters to and from panel members including invitations to annual panel meetings. There are also copies of correspondence between the 1997 External Advisory Panel on Education Chairman Jozef (Jo) M.M. Ritzen and de Ferranti and Bank President James Wolfensohn, including a facsimile on advice to the World Bank addressed to Wolfensohn and follow up thank you letters from Wolfensohn to Ritzen and other panel members.
  A variety of records are filed with the advisory panel correspondence including: Terms of Reference for the panels; panel meeting agenda; meeting draft conclusions; preliminary and final panel reports; Ritzen?s speech on reforming education to the World Bank Forum; transcript of the newly formed Human Development Network (HDN) kick-off meeting between de Ferranti and Wolfensohn; agenda and summaries of meetings including sector board meetings and correspondence related to the board's functions regarding the panels; hard copy presentation slides; addresses by Wolfensohn and senior management; issues papers; education sector booklet and other promotional material; external articles and newsletters; two copies of the 1978 panel report, one bound copy, kept by O'Rourke; and agenda with outgoing letters of invitation sent by O'Rourke for the high-level UNESCO meeting on the future of educational statistics and indicators hosted by the Bank. Following O'Rourke?s departure as director in 2000, Acting Director Marlaine Lockheed and HDNED Operations Officer Sobhana Sosale were involved in panel selection and meeting preparations, later under the direction of Ruth Kagia who began her tenure as director in early 2001. There is a small volume of mostly administrative correspondence from this period to 2003, including internal email hard copies and letters to panel members.
  Education Sector Strategy Paper
  There are also records in the series (1997 - 1999) regarding the preparation of the [Education Sector Strategy]( https://documents.worldbank.org/en/publication/documents-reports/documentdetail/406991468178765170/education-sector-strategy) issued in 1999 to shape policy and practice in member countries. Records were primarily maintained by Director O'Rourke, Adviser Jeffrey Waite, and Projects Assistant Anja Robakowski-Van Stralen. Record types include handwritten notes, concept papers, preliminary outlines and drafts beginning from late 1997, several with annotations, and the draft final report submitted to the Board of Executive Directors' meeting (1999). Correspondence is in the form of hard copy emails and occasionally internal memoranda primarily to and from O'Rourke and Waite containing comments from the sector board, external individuals, executive directors, and other Bank department staff including from the regions and the Operations Evaluation Department (OED). There is also an OED evaluative report and Committee on Development Effectiveness (CODE) informal subcommittee review meeting summaries, as well as correspondence and outlines of plans for strategy development, such as the timeline for implementation of the sector strategy work in the regions. Also included are O'Rourke's memoranda to the Operations Policy Committee presenting the paper and data collected, summaries of meetings with HDNED staff and regional staff to discuss the strategy paper, and summaries of other meetings such as with Wolfensohn regarding the status of education in the regions.
  Annual reviews
  A small portion of records in the series contains correspondence related to the internal review of Bank policy in the education and employment sectors (1983 - 1986), including copies of the operations annual review, Sector and Operations Vice Presidency (OSP) annual sector review, and Operations Evaluation Department (OED) annual reviews. Among the correspondence are draft reports and papers used for background and reference material.
  NRIC policy reports and documents
  Finally, there are four general policy files originally maintained in the NRIC that contain various reports and other records produced by Education Department (EDC) senior staff, consultants, and others (1978 - 1980). Included in the files are: OED Review of Bank Operations in the Education Sector (1978); Education Sector Policy Report No. 2680 (1979); Policy Review Committee Staff level review meeting on the Education Department, Central Projects Staff Education Sector Policy Paper (1979) and policy paper discussion drafts (1978 - 1979); Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO) and World Bank Cooperative Program "Training Equipment Lists in Food and Agriculture" publication with a forward by Habte (1978); and the publication entitled "Occupational structures of industries" by Manuel Zymelman (1980) containing country tables and industry tables.
  Records are arranged by subject. External advisory panel records are arranged chronologically.
  Certain "series" of records originally maintained in the semi-centralized Non-Regional Information Center (NRIC) that relate to a specific function or unit, in this case the Education Sector Advisory Panel file and Education Policy Documents, were arranged in this series.
  Most records were transferred to the Archives by the Human Development Network Education Team (HDNED) and previous units in multiple transfers between 1992 and 2011, in accordance with approved records retention schedules. The 1978 advisory panel and other operational policy records were originally sent by the sector to the Bank?s semi-centralized Non-Regional Information Center (NRIC) from the late 1970s until the NRIC's closure in 1987. These records were transferred from the NRIC to the Archives in 1994.
  * See Records of the Education Sector - Director and Front Office records ([WB IBRD/IDA WB_IBRD/IDA_88-01](https://archivesholdings.worldbank.org/director-and-front-office-records-1)) for records related to oversight and direction of policy work and sector strategy, global programs, and activities of the implementation adviser and Education Policy Division.
  * See Records of the Education Sector - Partnerships and program collaboration ([WB IBRD/IDA WB_IBRD/IDA_88-02](https://archivesholdings.worldbank.org/partnerships-and-program-collaboration)) for records detailing the Bank's partnership with UNESCO and other external organizations in the education sector.
  * See Central Files - Operational sector files ([WB IBRD/IDA ADMCF-07](https://archivesholdings.worldbank.org/operational-sector-files)) for records related to sector lending policy and sector papers that were maintained in the centralized filing system from the time of the establishment of the Education Division, Projects Department (PRJED) in 1965 until recordkeeping was decentralized in 1987.
  * See World Bank Group [Documents & Reports](https://documents.worldbank.org/en/publication/documents-reports) repository for digitized sector policy and other reports.
  - United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization [UNESCO] - Guidelines for Project Preparation Mission - Current Research in Building Materials and Low-Cost Housing in Sub-Sahara Africa - Office of Housing - United States Agency, 2022-12-14; 01104587
  - United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization [UNESCO] - Guidelines for Project Preparation Mission - Schools Construction Research and Guidelines - Briefing Note - Relations in the Education Sector - January 22, 1988, 1988-01-22; 01104588
  - Basic equipment list - 16v, 1979-01-01 - ?; 01104586
  - Guidelines general - set, 1978-01-01 - 1983-12-31; 01104470
  - Architectural standards / countries A - Z - set, 1974-01-01 - 1979-12-31; 01104585
  - Data collection forms - set, 1977-01-01 - ?; 01104584
  - Project progress report forms - set, 1977-01-01 - ?; 01104583
  - Operational aids: architectural appraisal forms - 22v, 01104582
  - Operational guidelines - 31v, 1977-01-01 - 1985-12-31; 01104581
  - Analytical data - 8v, 01104580
  - Project completion report (PCR) - set, 1977-01-01 - ?; 01104574
  - Teacher's flow - set, 01104572
  - Education efficiency model - set, 1977-01-01 - ?; 01104573
  - Labor requirements model - set, 1975-01-01 - ?; 01104570
  - Guideline project preparation and presentation to Board - set, 1976-01-01 - ?; 01104569
  - Sector memo - set, 1975-01-01 - ?; 01104535
  - Education index - set, 1977-01-01 - ?; 01104568
  - Review of audit completion reports - set, 1978-01-01 - ?; 01104567
  - Guidelines for Mass Media - set, 1973-01-01 - ?; 01104566
  - EVE Science PIV to UNICEF - set, 01104565
  - Guideline for project preparation mission - set, 01104564
  - Users guide to forecast manpower requirements models - set, 01104563
  - Project management arrangement trend - set, 1981-01-01 - ?; 01104562
  - Educational guideline and other policy and operational documents for education sector studies - set, 1981-01-01 - ?; 01104538
  - Guidelines for sector surveys PIMS and project appraisal in health professional training - set, 1973-01-01 - ?; 01104524
  - Users guide to teacher's requirement - set, 1975-01-01 - ?; 01104523
  - Checklist for the appraisal of nonformal education in Bank project - set, 1975-01-01 - ?; 01104513
  - Distribution of projects cost by Outley and DeLois - set, 01104512
  - Review of education lending FY74-78 and FY79-83 - set, 1973-07-01 - 1983-07-01; 01104510
  - User's guide for educational planning - set, 1977-01-01 - 1983-12-31; 01104511
  - Summary list of projects - set, 01104476
  - World Bank education and manpower model documentation - set, 01104471
  - Task Force on Bridging the Digital Divide Though Education - Correspondence, 2000-03-01 - 2000-07-01; 01678188
  - Special Grant Program - Proposed March 5, 1996 - Correspondence, 1997-01-01 - 1997-03-31; 01678184
  - Professional Expertise Profile - Correspondence, 1997-04-01 - 1998-05-31; 01678183
  - Monitoring the Progress of the Human Development (HD) Network - Correspondence, 1997-07-01 - 1998-01-31; 01678172
  - Education for All (EFA) in Latin America and Caribbean Region (LAC) - Correspondence, 2000-09-01 - 2000-10-01; 01678144
  - Africa Region - Country Action Plans for Education - Correspondence, 1997-05-01 - 1997-07-01; 01678104
  - Girls Education - Development Assistance Committee (DAC) Goals - Correspondence, 1996-08-01 - 1997-01-31; 01678179
  - Education Action Plan - Correspondence 2, 1997-07-01 - 1997-07-31; 01678117
  - Education Action Plan - Correspondence 1, 2001-08-01 - 2001-08-31; 01678116
  - Africa Region - Education Sector Overview - Correspondence, 1996-05-01 - 1997-01-31; 01678105
  - Education for All (EFA) - Post Dakar Actions - Correspondence, 2000-03-01 - 2000-12-01; 01678171
  - Commitments on Education for All (EFA) - Correspondence, 1990-03-01 - 2000-05-01; 01678146
  - Education for ALL (EFA) - Fast Track Papers - Correspondence, 2000-04-01 - 2000-10-01; 01678123
  - EDT research material: annual review of lending sector work, FY84-85 - box, 1983-01-01 - ?; 01125166
  - EDT research material: annual review of lending sector work, FY84-85 - box, 1983-01-01 - ?; 01125165
  - Education Sector Strategy Paper - Strategy Development - 2v, 1997-01-01 - 1999-12-31; 01573703
  - Education Sector Strategy Paper - Drafts, Comments - 1v, 1998-01-01 - 1999-12-31; 01573702
  - Education Sector Strategy Paper - Drafts - 2v, 1998-01-01 - 1999-12-31; 01573700
  - Education Sector Strategy Paper - Drafts, Substantive Correspondence - 1v, 1997-01-01 - 1999-12-31; 01573698
  - External Advisory Panel - 1996 - 1998, 1996-04-09 - 2003-01-11; 30123527
  - External Advisory Panel - 1978, 1978-10-31 - 1996-01-08; 30123526
  - External Advisory Panel - 2000, 2000-01-11 - 2002-12-05; 30123525
  - External Advisory Panel on Education - Correspondence 2, 1996-04-01 - 1998-03-31; 01678222
  - External Advisory Panel on Education - Correspondence 1, 1997-03-01 - 1999-03-31; 01678221
  - External Advisory Panel - Correspondence, 1998-10-01 - 1999-07-01; 01678201
  - External Advisory Panel - Documents and Correspondence - Correspondence, 1997-11-01 - 1998-12-01; 01678199
  - External Advisory Panel - Meetings 1997 - Correspondence, 1997-02-01 - 1997-03-03; 01678191
  - External Advisory Panel - Mini Summit - Education Group - 1996, 1996-04-30 - 1997-04-30; 30037782
  - External Advisory Panel on Education - 24 March 1997, 1997-03-24 - 1997-11-14; 30037781
  - External Advisory Panel - 1998 - 1999, 1998-05-01 - 1999-03-24; 30037780
  - Operational Policy - Education - PED - Policy Documents, 1978-01-01 - 1980-08-31; 01057489
  - Operational Policy - Education - PED - Policy Documents - Volume 2, 1978-01-01 - 1980-02-29; 30048552
  - Operational Policy - Education - PED - Policy Documents - Volume 1, 1978-09-01 - 1978-10-31; 30048668
  - Operational Policy - Education - PED - Policy Documents - Volume 3, 1978-02-01 - 1979-06-30; 30048676
  - Education - PED - Advisory Panel, 1978-01-26 - 1980-07-09; 01064414
  - Operational Policy - Education - PED - Policy Documents - Volume 5, 1978-11-30 - 1979-09-26; 30048678
  - Operational Policy - Education - PED - Policy Documents - Volume 4, 1978-08-01 - 1978-08-31; 30048677
  - United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization [UNESCO] - Guidelines for Project Preparation Mission - Educational Facilities - Schedule of Recommended Accommodation Units, 2022-12-14; 30462960
  - United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization [UNESCO] - Guidelines for Project Preparation Mission - Educational Building Report Number 15 - Design of Curriculum Development Centers - JP Hamel - 1979, 1979-01-01 - 1979-12-31; 30462961
  - United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization [UNESCO] - Guidelines for Project Preparation Mission - Furniture for Study Bedrooms, 2022-12-14; 30462962
  - United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization [UNESCO] - Guidelines for Project Preparation Mission - Guidelines for the Realization of the Aid Programme for the Construction of Primary Schools in Indonesia - 1975, 1975-01-01 - 1975-12-31; 30462963
  - United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization [UNESCO] - Guidelines for Project Preparation Mission - Clarification of the Construction Plan for Primary School Buildings, 2022-12-14; 30462964
  - United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization [UNESCO] - Guidelines for Project Preparation Mission - Preliminary Draft - Community Development and Popular Participation in Tanzania - Gothenburg - Krisno Nimpuno - March 1975, 1975-03-01 - 1975-03-31; 30462965
  - United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization [UNESCO] - Guidelines for Project Preparation Mission - Community Education Centers - Tanzania - Guidelines and Final Sketch Design - David Lewis - February 19, 1975 - 2 Copies, 1975-02-19; 30462966
  - United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization [UNESCO] - Guidelines for Project Preparation Mission - Comparative Analyses of Recent European Schools - David Lewis - March 19, 1976, 1976-03-19; 30462967
  - United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization [UNESCO] - Guidelines for Project Preparation Mission - Comprehensive Vocational Technical Education Training Facility - Synopsis, 2022-12-14; 30462968
  - United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization [UNESCO] - Guidelines for Project Preparation Mission - Guidelines for the Design of Curriculum Development Centers in the Asian Region - Preliminary Study - JP Hamel - September 1977, 1977-09-01 - 1977-09-30; 30462969
  - United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization [UNESCO] - Guidelines for Project Preparation Mission - Guidelines for Provision of Learning Equipment in IBRD - IDA Education Projects - Hursit Calika - M Hultin - August 17, 1972, 1972-08-17; 30462970
  - United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization [UNESCO] - Guidelines for Project Preparation Mission - Prototype Workshops and Laboratories for Technical and Vocational Education - Part 1 - Proposed Planning Methods - Draft Guide, 2022-12-14; 30462971
  - United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization [UNESCO] - Guidelines for Project Preparation Mission - Production Units and Technical Teacher Education - A Guide - October 1978, 1978-10-01 - 1978-10-31; 30462972
  - United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization [UNESCO] - Guidelines for Project Preparation Mission - Innovation in Management of Primary School Construction - Case Study - Educational Building Report - RD Srivastava - 1974, 1974-01-01 - 1974-12-31; 30462973
  - United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization [UNESCO] - Guidelines for Project Preparation Mission - Loan Financed residence in Universities - First Survey - University Grants Committee - Design Note Number 1 - May 1973, 1973-05-01 - 1973-05-31; 30462974
  - United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization [UNESCO] - Guidelines for Project Preparation Mission - Laboratories Investigation Unit Paper Number 4 - The Economics of Adaptability - PF Bottle Arics - 2 Copies, 2022-12-14; 30462975
  - United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization [UNESCO] - Guidelines for Project Preparation Mission - Planning Norms for University Buildings - Revised - February 1974, 1974-02-01 - 1974-02-28; 30462976
  - United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization [UNESCO] - Guidelines for Project Preparation Mission - Polytechnics - Planning for Development - Design Note 8, 2022-12-14; 30462977
  - United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization [UNESCO] - Guidelines for Project Preparation Mission - Primary and Village School Buildings and Teachers Houses - Report to Minister of Education of the Republic of Afghanistan - 1973, 1973-01-01 - 1973-12-31; 30462978
  - United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization [UNESCO] - Guidelines for Project Preparation Mission - Prototype - Cost Range Structure - 1976 - Report in Foreign Language, 1976-01-01 - 1976-12-31; 30462979
  - United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization [UNESCO] - Guidelines for Project Preparation Mission - Research on School Buildings - Central Building Research Institute, 2022-12-14; 30462980
  - United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization [UNESCO] - Guidelines for Project Preparation Mission - School Furniture Development - An Evaluation - FB Scriven and Associates - 1975, 1975-01-01 - 1975-12-31; 30462981
  - United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization [UNESCO] - Guidelines for Project Preparation Mission - Sudan - Low Cost School Building - Expanded Programme of Technical Assistance - BJ Kimmins - December 1965, 1965-12-01 - 1965-12-31; 30462982
  - United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization [UNESCO] - Guidelines for Project Preparation Mission - Techniques for Sulfur Surface Bonding for Low Cost Housing - Southwest Research Institute, 2022-12-14; 30462983
  - United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization [UNESCO] - Guidelines for Project Preparation Mission - Bid Evaluation Study - Volume 1 - A Norman and JG Perry - June 1978, 1978-06-01 - 1978-06-30; 30462984
  - United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization [UNESCO] - Guidelines for Project Preparation Mission - Guideline for Project Preparation Mission - May 1972, 1972-05-01 - 1972-05-31; 30462985
  - United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization [UNESCO] - Guidelines for Project Preparation Mission - August 1969 - Report in Foreign Language, 1969-08-01 - 1969-08-31; 30462986